<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Alfie Chadwick</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Alfie Chadwick</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Using Taylor Series to Improve the Euler Method: Part 1</title>
      <link>/2023/12/18/using-taylor-series-to-improve-the-euler-method-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2023/12/18/using-taylor-series-to-improve-the-euler-method-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Euler’s Method Higher Order ODEs Taylor Series Putting it together Euler’s Method Euler’s method is a classic way of approximating first-order differential equations. In short, it uses the derivative of a function and starting condition to estimate the value of the function a short distance from the starting point.&#xA;This is commonly written as:&#xA;\[ \frac{dy}{dx} = f(x, y) \] \[ y(x+h) = y(x) + hf(x, y(x)) + \epsilon \] \[ \lim_{h \to 0} |\epsilon| = 0 \]</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Drug Use in Communities</title>
      <link>/2023/10/22/modeling-drug-use-in-communities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2023/10/22/modeling-drug-use-in-communities/</guid>
      <description>Preface Introduction Aim Method Initial Model: SIR SUAR Model SAUR Model with age Simplified SUAR Model with age Results Discussion Conclusion References Appendix Appendix 1 : Stationary points of SIR model Appendix 2 : Stationary points of SUAR Appendix 3: Critical Points of Simplified SUAR model Appendix 4: Matlab code for generating conditional Stationary Points Appendix 5: Python code for simulating SIR model Appendix 6: Python code for simulating SUAR model Appendix 7: Python code for simulating 20 compartment SUAR model Appendix 8: Python code for simulating 5 compartment SUAR model Appendix 9: Python code for simulating 5 compartment dimensionless SUAR model Preface This was written as a University project but I’m pretty happy with how it turned out.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
