<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Visualizations on Alfie Chadwick</title>
    <link>/tags/visualizations/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Visualizations on Alfie Chadwick</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/visualizations/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Predicting the 2023 Hottest 100</title>
      <link>/2024/01/26/predicting-the-2023-hottest-100/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2024/01/26/predicting-the-2023-hottest-100/</guid>
      <description>Like many Australians, I spent my last Saturday in January getting hyped for the Triple J Hottest 100 countdown. And for the past few years, there has been a project run by 100 Warm Tunas that has been remarkably accurate at predicting the results of the countdown.&#xA;Warm Tunas makes predictions by scraping social media posts for people’s votes and then collating them as a sample of all votes. While this method is highly effective, I feel that it misses the point a bit when it comes to understanding why a song is popular.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new way to look at Categories in Hugo Blogs</title>
      <link>/2023/12/28/a-new-way-to-look-at-categories-in-hugo-blogs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/2023/12/28/a-new-way-to-look-at-categories-in-hugo-blogs/</guid>
      <description>This site is built through blogdown, which is a marvellous little R package that integrates Hugo sites into a R workflow. A nice thing about Hugo sites are the large number of themes available to quickly integrate with your site to change the vibe. My theme is mostly just a recolored version of the hello-friend-ng theme, using catppuccin for the colors.&#xA;My only gripe with the theme is that it uses a default list for all types of content.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
